Finding Aid for Department of Philosophy (University of Michigan) records, 1907-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Philosophy (University of Michigan) records, 1907-1987, 1947-1961
University of Michigan. Department of Philosophy.
1.5 linear foot
97113 Bimu 2
Departmental records mainly covering William Frankena's tenure as chairman (1947-1961); includes correspondence with students and faculty, course syllabi and exams, and photographs (1907-1932)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Department of Philosophy (donor #7137) in 1994-1995. 7137
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research.
The origin of the study of Philosophy at the University of Michigan can be traced back to the Catholepisterniad project in 1817, although the department was officially formed in 1837 with the founding of the University of Michigan. The curriculum was closely tied with religious principles as the first chairs and professors of the Philosophy Department hailed from the ranks of the clergy. Later, however, the curriculum and philosophical slant of the department was determined by the professors comprising the department's faculty.'
Consisting of fewer than six faculty up until the 1940's the Philosophy Department catered to a small number of students and was considered a distinguished program based upon the caliber of the faculty who sought to teach at the University of Michigan. Among outstanding philosophers who taught for the department are George Sylvester Morris, John Dewey, Robert Mark Wenley, Roy Wood Sellars, DeWitt H. Parker, C.H. Langford, Paul Henle, William Frankena, Charles Stevenson and Arthur Burks. These faculty members published various works in their respective fields of interests and were active in professional and academic circles.
In 197 1, the department had increased its faculty size to 20 and served approximately 60 students. Numerous searches took place to raise the ranks. Budget fluctuations called for the creation of visiting lecturer positions where professors from other institutions would serve one to two year stints at the University of Michigan. William Frankena observed this process from the other side as he took a sabbatical leave to serve as a visiting professor at Harvard University. Teaching fellowships, granted to graduate students were also another way of staffing lower level courses and providing assistance to the professors.
Enrollment in the Department of Philosophy's courses and program dropped during the 1970's encouraging the department to revise its offerings making them more accessible to non-Philosophy students and to develop alliances with other departments forming interdepartmental offerings.
Faculty members were active in campus affairs as well as in their own departmental activities. Department members frequently served on various University committees while also fulfilling their obligations to the department and the students. Great effort was expended in the placing of doctoral students in teaching positions across the United States resulting in or from outstanding relationships with colleagues at other universities.
For further information regarding the Department of Philosophy and its faculty, consult the papers of Arthur Burks, John Dewey, Arnold Kaufman, Alfred Lloyd, George Morris, Roy Wood Sellars, Charles Stevenson, Charles Bruce Vibbert, Robert Mark Wenley, and William Frankena, also located at the Bentley Historical Library.
Deans of the Department
1837-? Rev. John Monteith and Father Gabriel Richard
1869-1883 Rev. B.J. Cocker
1884-1889 George Sylvester Morris
1889-1894 John Dewey
1894-1996 Alfred Henry Lloyd
1926-1929 Robert Mark Wenley
1929-1947 DeWitt Parker
1947-1951 William Frankena
1961-1964 William Alston
1964-1977 Richard Brandt
1977-1979 Alvin Goldman
1979-1987 Jeqwon Kim
1987-1988 Allan F. Gibbard
1988-1993 Stephen Darwall
1993- Louis E. Loeb
Acting Deans of the Department
1949, 1971-1972 Charles Stevenson
1954 Irving Copi
1956-1957, 1962-1963 Paul Henle
1975-1976 Jaeqwon Kim
_________________
Sources:
Shaw, Wilfred B. The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, Vol. IV Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1944.
Brinkman, Ferol, Editor. The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, Vol. VI (1940-1975). Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1981.
The records of the Philosophy Department of the University of Michigan measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1907 to 1987 with many of the records dating from 1947 to 1961, coinciding with William Frankena's tenure as department chair. The record group has been arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material. Photographs of Department of Philosophy graduate students and faculty dating from 1907 to 1932 are available both within the collection and in an oversized folder.
The Correspondence files include information regarding personnel searches, scheduling, and various departmental business. Also included are letters between William Frankena and various acting department chairs who were serving during his sabbatical years. The Course Materials files consist of a sampling of exams and syllabi for several of the department's courses during the years 1947 to 1961 and 1984. Although this material is by no means inclusive of the department's offerings or representative of how the courses were taught over the years, it does provide some insight as to the department's expectations of the students.
The Student Placement files demonstrate the lengths to which the department as a whole went to secure positions for their graduating doctoral students. Correspondence regarding the special circumstances of several students are foldered separately and further show the support one could expect as a graduate of this department. An additional point of interest is the file of Michael Davis which illustrates the department's attitude towards censorship and the governing bodies of higher educational institutions.
The remaining files contain department minutes, personnel information, financial information, statistics, and various other bits of information that could help the researcher construct a picture of the department as it evolved during the 1950's to early 1980s time period.
The Photographs series consists of group prints (some outsize) of philosophy students and faculty.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; Philosophy.; Philosophy--Study and teaching.; Philosophy--Outlines, syllabi, etc.; Frankena, William K.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; Philosophy.; Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.; Parker, Dewitt Henry, 1885-1949.; Pillsbury, W. B. (Walter Bowers), 1872-1960.; Sellars, Roy Wood, 1880-1973; Vibbert, Charles Bruce, 1877-1950.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Records
  - Alston (William P.) Manuscript, "Illocutionary Acts" (Box 1)
  - Calendar Study, Response 1958 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Administration of the Degree Program in Religion and Ethics 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Program in Religious Study 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Committee Participation (Box 1)
  - Copi, Irving 1956-1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Admissions 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Carl Cohen 1957 (Box 1)
    - Course Scheduling 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Fellowships and Scholarships, 1954-62 (Box 1)
    - Interdepartmental 1951-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Kyoto Seminar 1955 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1951-1962 (Box 1)
    - Personnel 1956-1971 (Box 1)
    - Personnel Searches 1949-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Requests for Recommendations for Teaching Positions 1949-1962 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Lecturers 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - William Frankena and Paul Henle 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - William Frankena and William Alston (Box 1)
  - Course Materials
    - Ethics 1970 (Box 1)
    - Logic 1951 (Box 1)
    - Metaphysics undated (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 138 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 33, 1938-39 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 34 circa 1951-1960 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 61 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 63, nod. (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 103 1941 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 106 1947-1951 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 110 1950 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 129 1942 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 130 circa 1941-1959 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 141 1952 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 142 1950 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 174, nod. (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 181 1952 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 201 (Logic) 1984 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 202 1984 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 203, nod. (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 234 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 311, nod. (Box 1)
    - Philosophy 340 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Course Schedules 1959-1971, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Meeting Minutes 1956-1985, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Dissertation Title and Candidates 1950-1971 (Box 1)
  - Financial Aid Policy 1976 (Box 1)
  - Financial Items 1951-1966 (Box 1)
  - Grants 1950-1961 (Box 1)
  - Henle (Paul), Correspondence 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Department Information 1956-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Exam Requirements 1971 (Box 1)
  - Singer, Irving 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Statistics 1938-1974 (Box 1)
  - Student-Faculty Evaluations, Fall Term 1951 (Box 1)
  - Student-Faculty Evaluations, Raw Data, 1950-195 (Box 1)
  - Students, Guests 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Students, Placement Efforts
    - Bernard Harrison 1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, William Frankena 1956-1962, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Paul Henle 1951-1960 (Box 1)
    - Michael Davis, University of Nebraska 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Nelson Pike 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ranking Policy 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Fellows 1959-1960 (Box 1)
- Photographs 1907-1932
  - Class Photos
    - 1907-1908 (Box 1)
    - 1908-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1909-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1914 (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 1)
    - 1917-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1921 (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1925 (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1926 (Acolyte) (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1926-1927 (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1930 (Folder UBImum C26)
    - 1932 (Folder UBImum C26)
  - Lloyd, Alfred 1927 (Box 1)